Orcas.
Often known as killer whales.
They stalk the oceans of the world,
living up to their infamous name.
They hunt in groups
and use language to communicate.
With their high intelligence,
they leave a trail
of terror in their wake.
Now, it's they and not their prey
who are threatened.
Wildlife cameraman, David Reichert,
is determined to get intimately close
to this mighty predator
in its natural environment
to understand firsthand the relationship
between the orca and its prey.
In the southern Indian Ocean
midway between the coast of South Africa
and the Antarctic, lie the Crozet Islands.
This French archipelago sits smack
in the middle of the Roaring Forties.
Westerly winds that pack a real punch.
Here it rains 310 days a year.
Winds in excess of 60 miles an hour
for much of the year
make human life unbearable.
The wind brings rain, snow, and hail.
On the Crozet Islands, you can experience
all four seasons in less than a day.
September marks the beginning
of spring in the Southern Hemisphere,
but there's never a good time
to venture into this region.
Some people do.
This longline fishing boat
is after a catch
that can only be found in these waters.
Patagonian toothfish.
They were only discovered
at the turn of the last century.
Today, they fetch high prices
on dinner tables in Asia and America,
where they're more commonly known
as Chilean sea bass.
Other hunters prize the toothfish,
like the giant
of the dolphin family, the orca.
David Reichert is passionate about orcas
and intrigued by their behavior.
Like all the fish around here,
the toothfish fish
swim too deep for whales and dolphins.
But the amazing thing
is the orcas are such opportunists
that they've adapted to the presence
of longline boats in the area.
They've discovered an easy way to feed.
They only have to wait
for the lines to be pulled up.
Unfortunately,
a lot of pirate longliners are out there.
They're illegal and try to force
the orcas to keep their distance
by throwing dynamite at them.
So the orcas have become
rather cautious towards human beings,
even though they haven't given up
on the easy pickings.
Scientists have produced alarming figures.
Fifty percent of the orcas in the region
have disappeared in the last decade.
It's a wanton and secret slaughter
by men without scruples.
David boarded one of the few
legal longliners to get to the islands
and study the behavior
of this threatened mammal
in its natural environment.
As a specialist in filming marine mammals,
David stops at nothing
to get close to his subjects.
But what he's about to do
has never been attempted before.
Filming underwater close to boats
that present a threat to the orcas.
How nervous will they be of his presence
if private fishermen
have struck in the past?
A young female approaches,
naturally inquisitive.
Her mother instantly recalls her.
In orca society,
the young don't need to be told twice.
The orcas are certainly avoiding David.
He'll have to wait
until he gets to the Crozet Islands
for another encounter.
That's where the orcas are heading
because their traditional prey in the area
are not toothfish, but elephant seals.
Every spring,
elephant seals must return to dry land
to mate and give birth
after hunting at sea in the Antarctic.
Over thousands of years,
orcas have perfected
peculiar techniques to catch seals.
I wonder how far
the presence of the longline boats
has altered the orcas' culture
from generation to generation?
Has it changed their feeding habits?
What impact has the slaughter really had?
Has the elephant seal population
grown as the number of orcas declined?
To find out,
David will spend four hard months
alongside these animals
in conditions where life
is a daily struggle for survival.
Here animals are safe from man.
They shouldn't be afraid of people.
It's the perfect place
to study their world
and understand the close links
that unite predator and prey.
I've arrived just in time.
The elephant seals have begun to return.
This 15 foot male seal
has spent 10 months at sea,
gorging on fish
and squid in the Antarctic.
He's swum thousands of miles to get here.
Now, hauling four tons of blubber
onto dry land,
only one thing is on his mind.
Sex.
Enter a female.
But she's not here to mate.
Rather, to give birth to a pup
she conceived on the island last year.
For the male,
she's an irresistible image of Aphrodite.
To reproduce, males must establish
a harem and become the dominant male.
The only way to do that.
Throw your weight around
and impose yourself on other males.
The male is six or seven times
heavier than the female,
and to show he means business,
he bites her viciously.
How affectionate.
The dominant male must keep
his trophies away from prying rivals.
This potential rival
is already calculating the odds.
The role of dominant male
is highly coveted,
and on this beach,
there's only room for one.
Conflict is inevitable.
Another female arrives.
Distracted by the advances of two males,
she doesn't see the danger until too late.
Her long journey is over.
She'll never give birth to her pup.
Hunting this way shows how the orcas
have adapted to life around these islands.
Fish are rare and inaccessible,
so they must hunt marine mammals.
The rest of the family
has been alerted to the catch.
Allowing the others to join
the kill is a form of initiation,
especially for the young.
To survive, you must learn,
and the transmission of knowledge
is an essential part of orca culture.
This might seem cruel,
but it shows the extent
to which orcas are social animals
and how far they go to protect each other.
The fatal blow
is delivered by a young female.
Skuas and other scavenging birds
pluck raw protein straight from the sea.
Home away from home.
The wooden crate contains everything
David needs for his own survival
until the longline returns in four months.
Skuas confirm David's suspicions.
Animals on the Crozet Islands
have never been threatened by man.
They've no reason to be aggressive,
but every reason to be curious.
This is the price David
must pay to secure a front row seat
to study how orcas
and their prey interact.
Within a few days,
the dominant male elephant seal
succeeds in pressing
large numbers of female into his harem.
The problem now is to keep the peace.
It's time for a nap.
Others never seem to rest.
There's always a chance of a fat seal
may be napping close to the edge.
A large male orca with its typical
six-foot triangular dorsal fin
is followed by two females
with their smaller, curved fins.
Orcas live in a matriarchal society.
The dominant female leads the group,
comprised from her sisters,
daughters and other youngsters,
but never couples.
Reproduction only takes place
between separate groups.
The matriarch is very imposing.
Over 20 feet long.
I know orcas
have never been known to attack humans.
But what if she really is eyeing me
for her next meal?
The group moves off peacefully
to the south of the island.
David's close encounter
with the orca on land
reminds him of something
that happened on this beach in 1988.
Amateur footage of the drama,
seen around the world,
showed an inexperienced orca
becoming beached while hunting.
But scientists were on hand
to help it back into the water.
The female's release was a joy to behold
for both the scientists and the orcas.
A very lucky escape.
I wonder if the female
I encountered along the shore,
could be the same one
the scientists saved.
I felt threatened, but she may
only have wanted to make contact.
What do I really represent
to these super predators?
It's a question that dogs me.
This male seal knows only too well
what he represents for the orcas.
He recently barely escaped
becoming a meal.
Ironically, seals are more vulnerable
on land than they are at sea.
They dive to depths of over 4,000 feet,
far deeper than any orca.
In the shallows,
their thick layer of blubber
offer a tempting feast of protein.
No wonder orcas risk beaching
and hunting this way.
But even close to shore,
the elephant seal is no pushover.
A young orca strays from the group,
and finds itself face to face
with a powerful opponent.
The orca hazards a closer inspection.
The seal holds its ground.
No point in being too brave.
It was a good lesson for the youngster.
Next time, it'll stay with the group
where there's strength in numbers.
This male is staking out his territory
even though it hasn't found a single mate.
Hey, watch it.
Whoa, okay, calm down.
Loneliness is obviously getting to him.
It's time for me to explore the island.
I've decided to cross
the little volcano to the other side,
where I've noticed the orcas
disappear to a number of times.
What is it that attracts them down there?
This is the perfect spot for me.
The rocky bottom leaves the water clear,
and for once, the sea is calm.
What a treat
in this turbulent part of the world.
It's now obvious to David
what the orcas are after
on this side of the island.
A sloping beach shelters
a colony of king penguins
in their tens of thousands.
For the orcas, the beach represents
a well-stocked larder all year round.
Adult penguins
surround chicks born last year.
They'll keep their warm,
woolly coats for about nine months.
When they grow real feathers
and strong muscles,
they'll take to the sea
to feed themselves.
They wait patiently
for their parents to return with food.
There are plenty
of distractions to kill time.
They seem to have adopted me.
Probably because they're hungry.
Raising the young takes almost a year,
and requires
great devotion from the parents.
Mothers and fathers are away for ten days.
They swim hundreds of miles
to their hunting grounds
and dive 1,500 feet
to find fish and shellfish.
Once they filled their crop,
they return to their young,
picking them out from the crowd
by listening for their call.
King penguins
take to the sea together for protection.
This is an opportunity for orcas to refine
their coordinated hunting techniques.
First, they observe complete silence.
The hunters don't want
to sow panic among the penguins.
Then, moments before the attack,
they emit discrete clicks
to signal their position to each other.
When the trap is set,
the matriarch sounds the signal.
Catching a penguin demands
a lot of energy for little in return.
But they haven't much choice
if there's nothing else to hunt.
In summer, when the seals are abundant,
hunting penguins is good practice
for the leaner winter months.
For the penguins who managed
to break through enemy lines
to fish for their chicks,
the return journey
proves equally perilous.
Finally, starving chicks
are rewarded for their patience.
September draws to a close.
The dominant male now has
more than 100 females in his harem.
This record number probably
has something to do with the fact
that there are fewer orcas around.
But orcas keep piling on the pressure,
and for good reason.
Female seals are about
to give birth to tender pups.
Skuas and giant petrels
feast on the placenta.
And anxious mothers
make sure the placenta is all they get.
The first exchange of cries
between mother and baby are vital.
Along with their odor, this allows them
to identify each other in the colony.
With its eyes barely open,
baby seals feed off the richest milk
of any mammal in the world.
It contains ten times
more fat and calories than cow's milk.
Pups put on four times their weight
in only three weeks.
After that, mother's job is done.
The dominant male tires of herding
ever more females into his harem.
Not only must he watch over them,
but he must fertilize them too.
This earthly paradise
comes with a price, starvation.
The dominant male stops eating
for the entire reproductive season.
He sheds 30 pounds every day
for two and a half months,
surviving on his winter reserves.
The ten months
spent feeding in Antarctica.
Single males lie in wait
for the slightest opportunity.
The presence of so many females
stimulates their own desire
to perpetuate their genes.
The dominant male cries foul.
His bulbous nose amplifies the protest.
The larger the nose,
the greater the show of virility.
It's a rude instrument of dissuasion
for the legions of young pretenders.
Seeing one intruder off
only lets another into the harem.
What a never ending battle to stay on top.
DNA studies show the dominant male
is far from being the father
of all the pups.
The hormonal urge
to mate leads to outright war.
Winner takes all
in a clash between titans.
When you get this close to these giants,
you can feel how much energy
goes into their drive
to pass on their genes.
It's a symbol of resistance
to the extreme conditions of the place.
A real fight for life.
I'm determined to experience the same kind
of intense contact with the orcas.
I'm going back
to the clear waters on the other side.
I recognize the matriarch
by her imposing size.
I see in the fullness
of her attention towards me
great experience
and certainly a knowledge of man.
Is she again the one
who was saved by the scientists?
I like to imagine she is.
I wish this moment would last forever.
I must find out more about her
and her pod.
Once again,
the orcas treat David with caution.
The orcas developed a complex culture
because they live so long.
Males live for about 50 years.
Females can survive into their 80s,
which explains
why their society is matriarchal.
Females have more experience.
These mammals are such efficient killers.
They only need to spend
10% of their time hunting.
Otherwise they rest,
play, and educate the young.
A process that can last 20 years.
Touching, caressing,
and talking maintains harmony.
Scientists now know
that orcas from the same region
share a common language,
and even more amazing,
every individual clan has its own dialect.
Frustrated on land,
David decides it's time for a dip.
He hopes to meet orcas
in their own territory
behind this bed of giant kelp.
Orcas never venture
into these underwater forests.
Solid stalks rise
120 feet from the bottom,
and could become
a lethal trap for the orcas.
Beyond the forest,
the matriarch sneaks up on David.
Her clicks signal her position
to the others waiting in the shadows.
The matriarch
is simply checking the visitor out.
Once again, the encounter is fleeting.
Caution and mistrust
seem to reign in the orcas.
The appearance of penguins means the orcas
must have retreated to a safe distance.
For David, their grace and agility
are well worth staying underwater
for a little longer.
Well, well, looks like I've got a visitor.
The single male has been well
and truly defeated by the dominant male.
Perhaps, next year he'll have more luck.
Even the strongest seals
don't become dominant
until they're at least eight years old.
Even then,
for no more than two years running.
The battle to dominate
exhausts them too much.
He may not look aggressive,
but he's still potentially dangerous.
There's no way
I can get into my tent tonight.
What a beautiful day for a change.
It does wonders for my mood.
Baby elephant seals pass their first days
close to the warm bellies
of their mothers.
What momentary bliss?
The atmosphere
on the beach is positively festive.
Orcas also take advantage
of the peace and quiet to sleep.
But the way they sleep is most unusual.
So they don't drown,
evolution has blessed them
with an extraordinary trait.
Only half their brain sleeps at one time.
They literally nap with one eye open.
No sooner has the sun come out,
than spring is on the back burner again.
The Roaring Forties
return with a vengeance.
Wisely, the orcas move away from shore.
I wonder how the newborn elephant seals
are coping with the weather.
The pups keep on suckling
as though nothing was wrong.
It is really picking up.
I'd better seek some shelter.
Filming in these conditions
leaves me paralyzed with cold.
Without the tent, I'd be finished.
Suddenly, I feel very alone.
Very different from the animals.
I'm fragile and vulnerable.
The storm turns
the beach into another world,
or the end of the world.
There seems no limit to the power
of the elements on the Crozet Islands.
I've spent the night terrified
by the thought my tent would blow away.
By mid-October,
the first female elephant seals
to have arrived from the Antarctic
are now ready to return.
After nursing their pups for three weeks,
they're pregnant again
and will give birth here in a year's time.
This one is ready to leave,
but her pup isn't.
Abandonment before weaning seems cruel.
But there's a good reason.
Mother no longer has the reserves
to continue producing milk,
though she might return
after putting on weight.
But time is not on her side.
She's exhausted and vulnerable.
Orcas share the spoils of hunting.
Solidarity within the group
is a cardinal virtue.
The pup too is a victim.
How will it survive without its mother?
Unlike penguin chicks
that can count on both parents for food,
baby seals depend solely on their mothers.
Weak and skinny,
the orphan barely has a chance,
even against a bird.
It must find another mother.
The door is closed.
Female seals cannot afford
to feed two pups at once,
and other pups also insist
on exclusive rights to their mothers.
I'm heartbroken to see firsthand
the tragedy of this pup's life.
But there's nothing I can do to help.
It's been attacked
and rejected by its own species.
A victim of the cruel laws
of natural selection.
It will never know the taste of fish.
Will never become a dominant male
to father offspring
on this island at the end of the world.
Mid-November and the harem
dissolves like snow in the sun.
The dominant male rouses himself
one last time to perform his duty.
Babies are now
fully weaned and independent.
The young stick together
and discover the joys of infancy.
They've begun to molt.
Black at birth,
their fur has turned light gray,
but the new coats itch terribly.
David can't resist lending a hand.
After all, they've been neighbors
for nearly four months.
I know, it's not very scientific of me,
but I just can't resist
these furry, little bodies.
My excuse is that they, and not I,
made the first move into my camp.
I'm really excited by their willingness
to let me into their lives.
The seals really have accepted me.
What an honor.
The confidence they show
in me and the games they share
are the simplest and most important
forms of communication.
Moments like this
take me back to my own childhood.
By December, hunger forces
the young seals into troubled waters.
Their first tentative steps
are harmless enough.
But unlike young orcas,
they can't rely on adult protection
and education to survive.
For some,
the baptism will be ruthlessly short.
Orcas must fatten up for the winter ahead
when measly penguins
will be all that's left on the menu,
unless they brave the dynamite
to steal toothfish from the longliners.
David must catch the young seals
in the water for the first time
before they too migrate to the Antarctic.
I was looking for him,
but in the end, he found me.
Is he admiring me or mocking me
for needing this ridiculous suit
to enter his world?
But who's to say we can't be friends?
If only he would stay.
Why is he leaving?
Will he be back?
The answer is in black and white.
Is she hoping to catch my seal friend?
A male approaches me for the first time.
He's nearly 30 feet long
and weighs more than eight tons.
A living juggernaut.
Then the matriarch returns.
This time I'm sure
it's to make real contact.
I feel naked and completely defenseless.
The orcas know it too,
and I'm counting on their wisdom now.
We are communicating.
I don't know how exactly,
but it's pretty intense.
In this open, smiling face, I realize
we have both exorcized our mutual fears.
Call it intuition,
but I'm now positive this female
is the one saved from the beach long ago.
She's become head of the clan
and wants to know more about me
before exposing
the others to potential danger.
Today, she knows I come in peace.
No words can express the emotion I feel
in such a sublime moment of contact.
The orcas we sometimes call killer whales,
may be in their own way,
trying to thank us
for saving one of their own.
I'm reassured to see
how the orcas of the Crozet Islands
are preserving their ancient ways.
For now, at least,
in spite of the longliners.
Given their experience
at the hands of the pirates,
their initial reaction
to me was to be cautious.
How can you blame them
when faced with such a destructive species
as humankind?
Even when
their future is threatened by us,
they show
just how discriminating they are.
They opened the door
of their kingdom to me.
On an island, where life hangs
in the balance every moment,
wild animals accept my presence.
They give up some of their secrets,
and embrace me with full confidence.
This extraordinary encounter
has changed me.
Forever.